All right.
We'll get started.
Sorry, the lecture slides for this lecture were not
up earlier today, but it is now up.
So if you want to have that at your fingertips to look at,
you should be able to get it through the course website.
But if not, it's definitely up there on the GitHub.
Today, we're going to talk about what I think of as more
advanced architecture ideas.
So last lecture was really about the basic Transformer
and how we might tweak different parts of the basic Transformer
to get to a modern language model.
Now, I want to talk about things that I think
are much more advanced, much more complex
developments on top of the usual Transformer.
And the two things I'll talk about today--
the first one is attention alternatives, ways
of going to much longer contexts using architectural changes
that, for the most part, generally allow for linear time
dependence on the length of the sequence rather than quadratic.
The second thing I want to talk about
is the idea of mixture of experts.
So the first part is modifying the attention block.
The second part is going to be modifying the MLP part.
A mixture of experts are going to give us significantly better
utilization in terms of our hardware,
in terms of having more parameters
relative to the compute that we have to spend on these models.
So those are the two parts and the two ideas for today.
So I'm going to start with attention.
And I'm going to set the stage.
It's clear now that people want longer context length.
You want to pack a lot of things into the context,
so that your model has more knowledge.
Maybe it's an agent and operates on lots of things.
If you look at different models over time
on the x-axis over here, and the context window size,
this is in log scale, there's really a clear rush
by a lot of the top LLM vendors that
provide larger and larger context
sizes to support these kinds of more complex workloads.
Now, how do we control these costs?
Not yet.
The right plot also shows the ratio
between how much compute cost is spent
in the feed forward part of the network versus the attention
part of the network as you increase the sequence length.
And you see that the feed forward,
fairly large at the start, but grows linearly. Attention
It's an all to all connection between all
the different positions, quadratic, so quickly outpaces
feed forward as the sequence length grows.
So it used to be that for big models,
that smaller sequence lengths, feed forward
was the dominant cost.
As you go to these longer sequence lengths,
attention increasingly becomes more and more of a problem.
Now, what's the basic toolkit by which we can control these?
We've already talked about these.
Well, we talked about one of these,
and we will talk about another one of these.
We can basically take things like local attention
and combine them in different kinds of hybrid ways
to control the very high cost of global attention.
If you're only doing global attention once
every eight layers, and all the other ones
are these very local attentions, you've very much controlled the cost.
The other thing you can do is systems engineering.
I think a very underappreciated fact is, constant factors
really, really matter.
Part of the theme of this course is,
you need to pay attention to the details.
And it's very easy for people trained
in a more classical theory-oriented computer science
tradition to be like, yes, it's the big O that matters,
linear or quadratic.
But I think one of the biggest things that
has happened to context and attention cost
is flash attention.
Flash attention, we'll talk about this in a lot more detail
once we get to the systems lecture and as you do,
the systems assignments.
But FlashAttention is really just a very clever way
of rearranging the attention operation
into a much more systems-friendly way,
to minimize memory transfer overhead.
And by doing so, you can get truly, truly dramatic
improvements in the performance of your attention.
So base PyTorch is this blue.
You can just look at some of the shorter sequence lengths.
You're doing 30 to 40 teraflops per second.
And then you do FlashAttention, which
is really a constant factor systems improvement.
And you're getting these big, big improvements,
factors of 2 improvements.
And at some sizes, you can't even fit this in memory anymore.
But with FlashAttention, where you're not
materializing these big attention matrices anymore,
you can continue to run these, albeit somewhat slowly.
This doesn't fix any of the quadratic cost issues,
but constant factors are very, very powerful.
Now, that said, if we're going to 5, 10 million tokens,
these tricks might not be enough.
We want much more radical, much larger
gains in our ability to handle long context.
So this leads us to the question,
is there ways for us to have linear time or linear dependence
on the length of the sequence?
And what would those kinds of things look like?
There you go.
It turns out that a lot of people
have tried a lot of different things over the years.
And I think there are a few false starts.
But in the recent years, I would say, the last two-ish years,
there's been an emergence of a set of recipes
that are fairly effective in linear time attention, that
are now battle-tested at scale.
And that's why this is finally the first year when
I'm talking about linear time attention,
because it's clear now that these things really
work at scale, and in production, and so on.
To really explain all of these different methods that
work well, I think you need to really only understand
one core idea to start with, and then we're
going to elaborate and build upon that idea.
And that idea to start with is the associativity
of multiplication.
So let's think about how attention works.
We can write it in this compact notation, where
we say, the attention operation is going to be of Q, Ks, and Vs,
with these matrix dimensions up here.
And I'm going to take my Qs and the Ks,
and I'm going to have an all to all interaction.
All the n positions are going to interact with each other
by matrix multiplication.
And then I'll normalize them through a softmax,
this row over here.
And then I will multiply it with my values
V to get the attention outputs.
This is a classic self-attention or whatever other attention
operation.
Now, for the moment, let's forget
that attention has a softmax.
And then I'm just going to drop the row.
Forget it for the moment.
Now, if we didn't have a row, maybe we
can actually change the complexity of this operation.
So if you look at attention, it's
n squared dk, because we're taking this QK transpose
multiplication.
But if Rho was the identity, I can just move the parentheses
around a little bit.
And I can say, all right, instead of QK transpose
V, really, what I'm going to have is QK transpose V.
And if we do this reordering, well, we've
changed which part is quadratic.
Instead of having the n squareds,
which were pretty terrible, because these n's are very big.
They're millions.
It's the context length.
Instead, I can have dependence on n d_v d_k.
So now, we're multiplying essentially,
the key and the value dimensions.
These could be big, in principle.
I can have a big model.
But these are usually on the order of thousands,
tens of thousands.
No one has a million coordinates in their hidden dimensions.
And so this is a much more favorable term
to be dependent on compared to this n squared term
when we were doing this original attention operation.
So this is the first thing that you should know,
which is like, associativity of multiplication
allows us to change the dependence on the sequence length.
Now, the other thing that we can do now
is, if we consider this reordering,
this Q K transpose V, something that's even nicer about this,
and I think this has led to really, a lot of the research
that I'm going to mention in the next couple of slides,
is that this matrix multiply on the right,
in the self-attention case, looks just like an RNN.
Instead of writing it in this dense form up here,
I can write it incrementally.
As I sweep left to right on my context,
I can multiply my Ks and Vs, and I can update this thing
S, which is a state, and I can add it to my previous state.
This is incrementally multiplying and accumulating my KVs.
And I can multiply it with my Q to get my output.
And this dense operation up here and this RNN form
are equivalent.
And so what have we done?
Well, we've started from linear attention on the top left.
And then we've somehow gotten something that
looks very much like an RNN.
And what's nice about RNNs?
Well, RNNs are quite nice, because at inference time,
I have this S, which is my state, it's fixed in size.
And I'm just carrying that forward and forward.
So RNNs are very nice for inference reasons.
They are not nice for training reasons.
But the nice thing about linear attention
is, you can use them in either way.
You can have it in this dense form, which
will be great for training.
It's parallel.
Or you can have it in this serial form,
like an RNN, which is great for inference.
So you can get the best of both worlds.
Now, at least in terms of dependence of all these objects,
this is great.
This is lovely.
Unfortunately, this is linear, which is not very good.
This is really the starting point of our discussion.
Any questions so far?
This is really the basics.
One cool thing is, there have been people that have basically
used this linear attention as part of their attention
mechanism.
So Minimax M1, which is a fairly large scale, fairly
high-performance Chinese open model, uses a 7 to 1
hybrid, so seven linear attention layers plus one
full softmax attention.
Performance, generally strong.
You can compare it to a number of strong models
like OpenAI's O3 or DeepSeek-R1, fairly competitive.
And then since it's linear attention,
most of the dependence on context length is linear.
It's not fully linear, because you've got these softmaxes,
but the dependence is much, much milder.
So this is one example, where people
have shown that even this basic linear attention, which
is very, very simple to understand,
can be used fairly effectively at scale, as long as you've
got some full quadratic connections involved.
No one has, thus far, really proven out fully linear time
attention mechanisms at scale.
Everything that I'm going to talk about in the next couple
of slides is a hybrid.
So now, we've done linear attention.
But you might say, linear attention
is too naive and simple for me.
This is not what I want.
I want some more serious complex neural network stuff
to be happening.
Well, what you can now do is--
oh, sorry, I went a little too far, look
at the RNN form of linear attention.
So I've put the linear attention equation right here,
just so you don't have to keep going back and forth.
And we can add a small elaboration to linear attention
in order to get more expressive updates.
And this is how you end up getting Mamba-2.
Some of you may have heard of Mamba, Mamba-2, Mamba-3 now,
I think.
These are a family of state space models
by Albert Gu, and Tri Dao, and friends.
And they're derived, originally, from this state space
theory and view.
But actually, if you look at the mechanics of what is being done,
you can actually see it as a very simple elaboration
of the linear attention mechanism.
And so the idea is the following.
So we start with linear attention.
And you might say, really, the main problem
with linear attention is that I'm always
passing my state forward.
We know, from the olden days of LSTMs,
that it's important to when to pass information forward
and when to just not pass information forward,
to forget things and send them to 0.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm going to be inspired by that.
And I'm going to add a gate, gamma of t.
Gamma of t is not stateful.
Gamma of t only depends on my current inputs x of t.
And gamma of t is going to modulate how much of my state
I'm going to carry forward into the future.
Now, if you think about this, the state-dependent terms
are all these Ss.
This gamma is not state-dependent at all,
so this means that this is very simple to compute.
And there's still this duality.
You can compute this Mamba-2 term,
either as a big dense matrix multiply or at inference time,
use it in this recurrent form to get nice inference improvements.
So that's the core conceit or view of this idea
that you can either use it in parallel or sequence,
just like linear attention.
And people have now used this at scale.
So Nemotron-3, I mentioned briefly last lecture,
uses this idea of combining Mamba-2
as their lightweight layer.
And of course, you've got your big softmax attention
every now and then.
And they alternate this in various ways
to manage their inference cost, expressiveness trade-off.
Nemotron-3 achieves pretty good performance
compared to Qwen3 thinking as compared to GPT OSS.
And because of all these Mamba-2 layers,
has pretty good throughput at fairly large context length.
So you can see that it works.
At least, these are small frontier models,
not really big frontier models, but small frontier
models that are open source.
Cool.
So now, we've built on this gating idea, which is cool.
You might say, though, can we just keep
pushing this idea further, and taking this recurrence,
and making it increasingly more complex?
And the rule of thumb, in some sense, for what you
can do with your operations here is, as long
as you're getting the various terms in your RNN,
so to speak, with only input-dependent terms,
so no state dependence, then you will still
have this fairly nice duality between parallel operations,
which you can use for training, and serial operations, which you
are going to use for inference.
So gated delta net is probably among the most widely
used, I would say, state space model now.
I think it's been tested in quite a few papers.
And there's a very nice large scale scale
up in 3.5 for these models.
So let me talk you through what gated delta net is
in comparison to Mamba-2.
So Mamba-2 is, as I have at the top here,
we take the linear recurrence, this state update.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to gate it with my gamma.
Oh, I forgot to explain this vt.
Sorry.
I apologize for that.
I added this for completeness.
Mamba-2 also has a modification, where
they add what is basically a residual layer to the yt update.
It's not really core to the state update or their arguments
for why this is a good idea, but I put it in for completeness,
just to make sure I'm actually giving the true Mamba-2 updates
rather than a more abridged version that only gets the core
ideas across.
But you can ignore the vt for now.
This is really just like an architectural improvement that's
not core to the state updates.
Gated delta net takes this idea in some sense and adds
a second gate, beta t.
So what does beta t do?
Beta t, I think of as a no input operation gate.
If beta t is 0, that basically means,
don't take any of my current information,
don't add it into my state.
And I think, most or all of you are probably
familiar with LSTMs.
This is very reminiscent of the ideas in LSTM.
You've got gates that control whether to forget
and whether to put in information from the current time step.
So it operates in a very similar set of principles,
although, of course, derived, I think, originally
in a very different way.
Now, the other thing that's interesting about gated delta
net, and this comes from the delta net rather than
the gated delta net, is this update direction.
So instead of just gating things,
you could have made this 1 minus beta t, for example.
What they do is, if you're going to do an update,
where you're putting in this beta, what you're going to do
is, you're going to try to project out,
in some sense, my current key direction.
So the intuition here is, I'm going
to be writing in information from my current key, k of t.
And when doing that, not only do I
want to put in new information, I also
want to erase any previous keys that have gone into it.
That's one way that you can think about updates--
not just put stuff in, I want to clear out the current key that
has gone in.
And that's why there's this blue term, this identity
minus beta t k t k t transpose, which is essentially
acting as a projector that is projecting out
things in the kt dimension.
That's not exactly right, because you're not doing things
like unit normalization, but you get roughly the intuition here.
The other thing I'll mention before--
oops, sorry, I have this blue box here, I'll
move on with beta delta net, is that this
has been reinvented, in some ways, in various settings.
This update, this projector appears
if you try to solve certain kinds of meta
learning least squares problems.
It's been reinvented in other forms in fast weight programming
or test time training, where essentially,
through very different design principles,
researchers from those areas have basically
ended up with the exact same kinds of solutions.
And the thing that I'll say here is, the Qwen 3.5 and the Qwen
Next models that were predecessors to that,
some of the best open source models available today.
And they use exactly this architecture.
They use a 3 to 1 gated delta net attention hybrid.
Very reasonable performance, strong inference characteristics
that you can see on the right there.
Qwen Next has much higher decoding throughput
relative to Qwen 3 as the context length goes up
and up and up.
The middle panel is a comparison of performance
versus various closed-source models and previous generation
models.
This hybrid architecture doesn't seem to hurt performance
very much at all.
The last thing that I will say is,
there haven't been that many great controlled studies of how
hybrid architectures perform.
There's maybe one by ByteDance Seed and UC Santa Cruz
folks, where they compared things like Mamba-2,
and gated delta net, and other architectures
as a function of how many hybrid layers you have.
Some of the results, I would say, are messy,
but the things that I would point at
is, this dashed line over here on this right panel,
this guy is full attention performance.
And as you go from left to right,
this is increasing the number of non-full attention layers.
So the RNN layers, let's call them,
you increase them as you go to the right,
and you see performance degradation.
But maybe the thing to see here is
that for some of the best architectures that you have--
the yellow, the orange, the blue,
these are like the gated delta nets and various other variants.
You see that at the low ratios, there's basically no hit.
And then once you pass a certain point,
you start to see more significant degradation
in long context performance, in this case.
Basically, at the end, as you go to full RNN,
you have very noticeable performance degradation
in all these architectures.
The same is true at various different other kinds
of evaluations.
Some of these, I think, have been
optimized by the architectures themselves.
Single key retrieval is a task that, I think,
all of these long context architectures
explicitly optimize for.
But if you look at QA performance,
we see the same story that as we increase
the amount of hybrid ratio, we see decreases
in performance, fairly steadily and fairly clearly,
ending up at this pure point.
Any questions for the linear time attention stuff?
I have one last efficient attention
thing to talk about, but yes.
[INAUDIBLE] look like the parallel form of attention
versus the linear form.
[INAUDIBLE] Shouldn't they be mathematically equivalent?
Yes.
Why do you see degradation in performance if you [INAUDIBLE]?
Sorry.
By recurrent, I meant RNN in general,
any recurrent formulation.
So gated delta net would be a recurrence.
That is not equivalent to this top one.
This is full softmax attention with the row.
The first step is lossy, where we drop the row,
and then we become linear.
That's the very, very first step of any of these.
So this part is going to be lossy.
And then after that, this linear form
to this recurrent form, this equivalence, that is exact.
Good.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] Oh, yes.
Yeah, this term, right?
Yeah.
So in the linear attention form, what we're really doing is,
we're taking these kv's, and we're
accumulating them with queues.
In the dual form, that's how this operates.
But you might actually want in your outputs
to also have some value from your current time step.
You might think that, oh, the value for my current time
step for my token is actually useful for various things
downstream.
And so this acts a little bit like a residual connection,
where the value of my current inputs
directly pass through to the outputs of my attention.
And D is another modulated gate, where
you can control the amount of pass through that happens.
Good.
OK.
So that's linear time attention.
There's a lot of really interesting stuff.
It's also interesting that a lot of the methods that
have gotten tested out really have
this nice, simple, linear attention style, recurrent form.
There's a few exceptions, but for the most part, a lot of this
has converged to almost very LSTM-like objects in the end.
What do I want to say?
OK.
So there's another alternative.
What I talked about was linear attention,
which has this very nice complexity theoretic flavor to it.
I want to talk about another attention optimization, which
I did not talk about, but falls into this family
of efficient attention things that are important.
So DeepSeek in DeepSeek 3.2, I think, had DSA, not Do Sparse
Attention, that's DeepSeek Attention, where what they do
is, instead of computing attention—
that was not intentional part, instead of computing attention
over all the tokens, what you're going to do
is you're going to first have a lightweight indexer that's going
to subset a bunch of tokens.
So you're going to look at your very long context.
And the indexer is going to pick out some subset of these, much
smaller than the full sequence.
And then you're going to do full attention on that smaller
subset.
So the mechanics of this are pretty simple,
at least in the forward pass, where what you do
is you have your normal Qs and Ks,
but then you pass this through this indexer.
And what the indexer does is, it takes the qk inner products,
it takes a ReLU.
And then it's going to have these weights that are derived
from the preceding tokens.
And then this is going to give you the activations for each
of the positions.
And then you're going to take this
through a top k, where some number of these top positions
get included into my attention computation.
And I'm going to do my usual attention computation that
emits a key value.
The nice thing about this is it's very, very sparse.
And if this indexer is lightweight,
now, this bottom term, where you're doing full attention,
can be done on a very small subset.
Another thing that both DSA and I
think, GLM show is that, you don't actually
have to train the model with this,
because training with this indexer thing
is maybe pretty annoying and very complex.
What you do is you just train a normal transformer.
And when you do your long context extension,
you actually then drop in this lightning indexer,
and then you train the model to handle this indexer
in an extension stage that's separate from pretraining.
So actually, the computational cost of doing this is itself,
pretty light.
And I want to highlight in DeepSeek's v3.2,
where they proposed DSA, this model is quite good.
The v3.2 matches all the other frontier models at the time,
like Claude 4.5 Sonnet or Gemini 3.
And they also have this very nice plot,
where they're showing, well, our prefill,
which is the attending to the input, and also decoding,
where you're actually generating, both of these
are very favorable scaling compared
to the previous generation of DeepSeek models
that did not use sparse attention.
And that makes sense.
If you're only paying attention to a very small subset,
you're going to dramatically be reducing
your costs of doing attention.
And I think another nice orthogonal validation of this GLM5, which came out last year.
I think GLM5 is one of the best open models that are available,
like period.
And they also adopted this DSA approach.
And they have actually fairly nice ablations in their paper
here, if you're curious, where they end up comparing with, oh,
what happens if we do DSA with some warm
up or just do DSA or don't do DSA at all?
The main thing that they're showing
is, if they do full DSA training,
you don't lose very much in performance
relative to full attention, even at long context retrieval
tasks that are fairly difficult to do with RNN style
architectures.
So this is a totally alternative view
of how to reduce attention costs.
Notice, I'll go back one slide, this is not linear time.
The indexer still has to operate on full all
to all attention, because you got these qk
inner products that are not going to be linear in cost.
But you can make this indexer much, much cheaper,
for example, by making this lower dimensional
or making this w very small.
All of this can be made much cheaper in its cost.
So that's a totally alternative view, works very well.
I won't talk much about this.
But it turns out that this idea of top k selection
is going to be core to the next part of this lecture.
I'll stop here for any efficient attention questions
before I move on to MoEs.
Yes.
So the indexer, the time complexity for that,
is it n squared?
Yeah.
I mean, in order to know what to select,
it does have to look at everything.
And there's no clever state transition
stuff that happens here.
It is really brute force inner products.
So if you're going through all of it,
then the step afterwards is also quadratic as well.
How are we getting time like [INAUDIBLE]?
I mean, it's like a system's trick, almost.
You're going to do the indexer much more lightweight.
And there are many ways to do that.
You can do that in much lower precision, which
they talk about.
You can do it in ways that are lower dimensional by projecting
the q's and k's further, just for the indexing.
So there are lots of tricks that you can do here,
that you can imagine, but the indexer
is going to be much more lightweight.
So the constant factors are very good.
And then for the second one, even though it's quadratic,
it's quadratic on a shorter context length,
because it's top k, we can control k.
So now, this is expensive but small.
So this is another one of these things
of, sometimes, don't get too stuck up on the quadratic versus
not.
Sometimes, the constant factors are really, really important.
There's another question?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] That's right.
Or it's part of a continued pretraining style thing,
because all the models, you don't train long contexts
from scratch for compute and various other reasons,
you train a short-ish context model first,
and then you've got these long context extension stages.
And so the nice idea here is that, we're going
to do the second phase anyway.
Why don't we bolt the long context cost savings
on at the same stage?
And it's surprising that it works.
Honestly, they can bolt on this frankly scary-looking TopK
non-differentiable object.
But as you'll see in the next part,
maybe you shouldn't be so scared of TopK selection.
[INAUDIBLE] So this is also part of the post
with other post-training steps?
Yeah.
The usual recipe that I am familiar with,
when a lot of the open source models, is it
usually goes like short context pre-training, long context extension, then post-training.
Yes.
Is the k here similar in length [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, that's right.
You would pick values that are much closer to short context
performance.
And you would bound it.
So regardless of the input size, they would be bounded.
Any questions?
OK.
Does the removal of softmax for [INAUDIBLE]
causing training instability?
Training stability issues.
That's a good question.
I don't think so.
I'm not aware of documented linear softmax causing
lots of attention.
If anything, softmaxes are usually
more of the problems for various reasons.
So I think this will actually improve the stability
properties of the architecture.
Can you predict the next [INAUDIBLE] attention?
Consider the [INAUDIBLE] attention mechanism requests,
because of the low computing cost and the low latency.
Given that you predict, I mean, in high level,
what kind of features that will be [INAUDIBLE] the [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
I don't know if I have good predictions for what
the future attention architecture looks like.
I mean, my somewhat cop out answer to this, I think a lot of this will look like we
throw all of these tricks in.
In the same way as the architectures have gotten
very complex by taking all of these successful recipes
and throwing them in, I think also
that there's an even broader layer or a higher level
layer of basically using post-training
to have the model manage its own context.
Compaction, retrieval, all of these things
are basically an added layer on top.
I think a lot of the work that I imagine
will be integration of these different layers,
because we've seen that, at least the linear time attention
stuff has converged a lot into LSTM-like
or linear attention-like architectures.
And I don't really see that changing too much
in the near future.
Cool.
Oh, yes.
One last question.
Can you speak about lower precision attention?
Is FP4 attention possible?
I think the indexer is partially motivated by things like this.
FP4 attention, definitely possible.
I think the drawback is that the loss of precision for things
like softmaxes, where small, underflow, overflow,
these kinds of things can really start to matter,
can, sometimes, be pretty problematic.
And so I think this motivation of saying
like, OK, let's do selection with low precision
and then do a full precision computation afterwards,
because then the value vectors can be more finely
added together and weighted together.
It's an approach that makes sense.
I don't know if there's really good ways
of doing full attention in FP4 or even
lower precision of some kind.
Yeah.
OK.
OK, one last question then, then I'll move on.
So compared to transformers, compared to state space models,
what's the downside of training more complicated state space
models?
Yeah.
So that's a good question.
There have to be some downside or otherwise everybody--
Well, the downside, I think, is expressive power.
The all to all connection in softmax
attention is incredibly powerful.
It's also very easy to train.
It used to be, I think, compared to say, an LSTM.
Attention had the very strong advantage
of hardware efficiency.
You could train in parallel.
I think the reason why the state space models have caught on,
despite their similarity to LSTMs
and similar drawbacks in terms of representational power,
is that now, there's this kind of well-understood duality
because of the linear attention thing
that I talked about, where you can go from this RNN form
to the more dense matrix multiply form.
And the matrix multiply form allows
for computational efficiency.
So that trade-off has now been checked off.
But you've still got the trade-off of,
if you have a finite state and you
have to carry everything through,
you're going to be losing some information relative to just
carrying everything.
[INAUDIBLE] is going to be a problem in state space.
So [INAUDIBLE] the context itself, [INAUDIBLE].
Well, in the state space, you have
to basically think about the context length
relative to the size of your state.
I mean, if you have a state the size of your context,
then you're good to go, but then you're
paying these very large costs.
So really, the point is, the free lunches,
if you want a really tiny state, it's
really hard to compress all the information in a big context.
It might be possible one day to not have any trade-offs,
but I think, thus far, that's where
the trade-offs are showing up.
Cool.
OK.
So now, I'm going to talk about mixture of experts.
And I think mixture of experts are important to talk about.
Conceptually, they don't really change the game.
One way of thinking about mixture of experts
is, they are just a more efficient MLP.
You take your MLP.
And somehow, someone gives you just a more efficient MLP.
That is what mixture of experts is.
But I think you need to understand
what mixture of experts is, I think,
for two reasons-- one is this slide of everyone's
doing MoEs these days, everyone's shipping MoEs these days.
You should understand what it is if you're
going to want to be people who deeply understand language
models and how they work.
So that's one reason.
The other reason is that MoEs actually
has some really interesting mechanical components to them.
If you look at how MoEs are built
and what primitives they use, you
will quickly see MoE like primitives in many places.
And you'll realize, wow, I can do more interesting things
with neural networks.
So there's a broader reason why I
think MoEs are interesting and cool,
and you should learn about them.
So what is an MoE?
MoEs are very simple things in some ways,
they're just replacements of your MLP.
So on the left is your usual MLP for a transformer.
You've got your attention.
You've got some normalization.
And then you've got a feed forward right after that.
This is where a lot of the dense, big information
processing happens.
Now, what I can do instead is, let's say, I take my big FFN.
And I'm going to cut them up into smaller FFNs.
So I now have four feed forward networks.
And actually, let's say, I don't cut them up into smaller pieces.
Let's say, they're the same size as my original FFN.
And somehow, by some magic, I have
a system that tells me which FFN to pick for every input.
Now, what I've done is, I have 4x the parameters,
or at least for my FFN, I have four FFNs worth of parameters.
But on any forward or backward pass,
I'm only going to pay one FFN worth of cost.
That's great.
So in some sense, the original motivations for MoEs,
if you read the original papers, have this very parameter-centric
view.
If you start something like, well,
let's say, you just wanted more parameters,
because you believe more parameters are good.
OK.
Good.
If we want more parameters, and we
don't want to pay the cost for more parameters,
you need something on the right.
So this is the mental model that you should have for MoEs.
You want to increase parameters without affecting your flops.
Now, why are they so popular?
Every model that you get on Hugging Face
or whatever these days are MoEs past a certain size.
Past a certain size, everything that you get seems to be an MoE.
And the reason is because it seems
to be the case that for whatever reason, if you keep
the total compute the same, but you just increase
the number of sparse parameters, somehow,
the models are generally getting better.
So this is evidence, maybe in favor of the view
that more parameters are, in fact,
generally good, even if only a subset of them are active
at a time.
And I'm going to refer to some of the original Google papers
extensively throughout this lecture.
This one's from Fedus, et al, in 2022, where they were doing,
I think, the switch transformer for this one.
And they're showing, oh, as you increase
the number of experts, so this is active parameter
stays the same, number of experts increases,
your test loss for language modeling
is just decreasing, decreasing, decreasing.
That's lovely if all you care about
is your forward pass flops.
On the right, you see similar things as you train faster.
As you increase your training compute on the x-axis,
if you have more experts for the same amount of training compute,
you just get better performance.
So for both training and inference,
MoEs just give you a free win.
This is pretty wonderful.
It's pretty great.
And this is really something that's been seen many times.
This is the same plot from before on the left
from the Fedus paper.
Last year.
I think, AIQ folks put out this OlMoE paper,
which was their open source mixture of experts
analysis and training paper.
And they see the same thing as well.
If you look at training loss, or validation loss,
or downstream benchmark performance,
you see that in training time, these models
are doing much better as MoEs compared
to their dense counterparts.
So something like two times faster or something like that,
training a MoE relative to a dense model.
So you can really see the benefits of sparsity here.
And I think the proof is in the pudding.
But if you look at all the MoEs that got released,
they are much stronger than dense models
in terms of activated parameters, which
is what matters if you care about inference flops,
or really, even just in general, the cost
to train and serve these systems, the all-in cost.
So in DeepSeek v2 and the earlier DeepSeekMoEs came out,
it was really a big shift from a lot of these dense models
that everyone else was training.
You saw that, wow, we have much fewer active parameters, just as
good, if not better MoE performance compared
to everyone else.
This is some really good stuff happening with MoEs.
Good.
OK.
So hopefully, I've convinced you that MoEs
are an interesting thing that you should spend your time
thinking about and studying.
Oh, great.
And then one last thing that I'll
say for why this is important is,
MoEs give you another axis of parallelization.
We'll talk about parallelization in systems in three more
lectures, I think.
But parallelization is actually one
of the really big important things in LLMs.
LLMs are very big.
They don't fit in single devices,
either to train or inference.
So you want many different ways of cutting up
your model to efficiently serve or train them.
Mixture of experts have this additional nice thing
that you can do, where your experts within each FFN
naturally come in different chunks.
Each expert is a natural chunk.
You can put them on different devices.
And then you can route the activations to different devices.
We'll talk about expert parallel later, which is what this is.
But this gives you an additional systems thing
that you can optimize, which is very helpful if you
want to optimize your serving.
In the West, I think there's been several open source
releases that are big, strong MoEs.
On the big model side, there was Llama 4 and GPT OSS from OpenAI.
Unfortunately, I guess, open source model releases
in the West have stalled, for the most part.
So there aren't quite as many being released now,
but there's at least two good examples of this,
both top tier models in their own right.
But I think a lot of the action for both MoE
research and training has happened in China.
Qwen, and DeepSeek, and some others, like mini CPM,
did some of the earliest work training and popularizing MoEs.
They continue to do really great work on MoEs.
If you look at some of the early Qwen MoE models,
this was Qwen 1.5 MoE.
They showed that their like small 2.7 billion parameter
active model was doing better than many of the 7B models
at the time.
And I think some of this early proof of work from DeepSeek
and Qwen really convinced everyone else in the open source
community that this was the right way to go.
Speaking of DeepSeek-- was there a question?
Yes.
I guess one question I had about the expert parallel,
isn't there like a communication bottleneck that's
built up because these experts are communicating
with each other?
Yes.
So in some sense, you pay the communication cost
of shipping an activation over.
And I will not explain, but I will show you one trick
of how you reduce that.
But in general, you're trading certain things off.
You're getting more aggregate flops.
You're reducing your memory use.
And in exchange, you're going to pay for comms.
So it's highly dependent on your topology and all
these other things, whether this is going to be a net win.
Cool.
Oh, yeah.
So during training [INAUDIBLE].
OK.
This is the important part.
During training, they are also sparse.
This is really the key thing that makes MoEs hard.
I mean, I'm spoilering the key idea from a few slides down,
but it would be very easy if we activated all the experts
during training.
Because then we get to see, oh, which
expert is good for my input?
So you get to learn how to route.
The hard thing about MoE is that during training, you only
have one or k experts active.
So you don't what happened with the rest of them.
You only know the ones that activated.
Despite this, you must somehow learn to route.
So it's got this RL bandit flavor to the problem,
but we're not going to solve it with either RL or bandits.
We're going to solve it with the power of heuristics
and deep learning magic.
Yes.
What is the granularity of switching between experts?
So the granularity, as in the scale at which we route experts,
is at token level.
I don't know if--OK, good.
Good.
That was the question.
Yes, at the token level.
So every token gets an expert.
And the routers, just to get your mental model correct,
the routers are super naive.
They're a single matrix multiply between your input
and your whatever.
And so you're not going to do anything complicated.
You don't know it's like a medical question or not.
You're like, oh, this is a token that looks like it's
in, I don't know, Japanese.
Let's route it to expert 7.
Yes.
Yeah.
So is there an upper limit to parallelizing these MoE models
in training or inference?
Yeah, in general, there's an upper limit to parallelization,
because as you shard over more and more devices,
the communication cost explodes.
Well, if we get the assignment to design done correctly,
you will have to deal with some of these in your assignment.
We will ask you to figure out the networking
topology and things like this that will make sharding make
sense, or it's the reverse.
Given a networking topology, you'll
have to figure out how to shard models and things like this.
Yeah.
Good.
DeepSeek，现在以 DeepSeek R1 等闻名。
但我觉得我真正喜欢 DeepSeek 的一点是——
最初，这门课原本是，我们就
过一遍 DeepSeek 论文的讲解，最早
那一版，是因为他们其实做了
很长时间里在 LLM 科学研究中非常好的架构工作。
而 DeepSeek 是较早一批
展示为什么 MoE 很好的工作之一。
他们在消融实验方面做了大量优秀的工作，比如，
如果我们使用稠密层会怎样？
如果我们使用哈希路由会怎样？
如果我们使用 switch router 会怎样？
所有这些不同的设计决策，
你可以在他们早期的一些 DeepSeekMoE 论文中看到。
所以如果你对这些问题感兴趣，
比如架构、设计等等，
我建议你读一读早期的 DeepSeek 论文。
从这些论文里能学到很多东西。
当然，进展并没有停止。
DeepSeek v3、v3.2，以及 GLM 等等，已经构建了这些
出色的、非常强大的 MoE 模型。
很明显，这就是
这些大模型未来发展的方向，
在可预见的未来。
至少我想接下来的几年，都会是 MoE。
好的。
那么现在的问题是，为什么它们没有更流行？
在很多方面，我觉得 MoE
被接受得相当慢。
你看看其中一些论文。
它们是 2022 年的。
Google 当时在研究并真正尝试推动 MoE。
但直到 2024 年之后，MoE 才真正
开始流行起来，为什么？
另外，如果你在做各种 LLM 研究，
你很可能主要使用的是稠密模型，
那为什么不用 MoE 模型呢，如果它们这么好？
我们可以节省计算。
MoE 带来了很多复杂性。
训练 MoE 或使用 MoE 并不容易，
or to do many things.
The infrastructure is very complex.
I mean, there were a couple questions about parallelization,
but this is generally right, that it's
hard to parallelize experts in ways that
are efficient in utilization.
MoEs have a lot of parameters.
It's hard to fit them on a single device.
And if you're training them, the MoEs can really blow up on you.
And you'll see why in a few slides,
why MoEs are just really hard to deal with,
but they're just not easy objects to work with.
I mean, there's good rules of thumb now, but it's not easy.
I'll briefly mention with one slide that there are people
that also mixture of experts, the attention block
in transformers.
There have been a couple of papers,
but they are much less common.
And I think the things that I have seen
is that they haven't been quite as
easy to tame or to get to work compared to just replacing
the FFN or the MLP layer.
So I'm only going to talk about the left.
This is basically what all the big models do.
People are not, for the most part, sharding or sorry,
splitting up attention heads into experts.
OK.
So that was the broad industrial overview of MoE
and what the state of things are.
But now, let's talk about how you design an MoE, how
you think about an MoE.
So to do that, I'm going to talk about three different kind
of axes of variation.
So what kinds of things can change for MoEs?
Well, you can change the routing function.
We know that MoEs have this core thing of a router
has to send tokens to experts.
So we can change that.
We can change the sizes of the different experts.
For a given budget, you might have more experts
with fewer parameters or fewer experts with more parameters.
And then finally, we're going to talk about training,
because training is going to be really difficult.
Once you start to realize how MoEs work, you realize, wow,
it is not easy to train something that routes
tokens to different places.
OK.
So in all cases, we don't want to activate all the experts.
We want to only have some subset of experts active.
And so we are going to always be choosing some TopK.
There are different kinds of choices that you can do.
You can have the token choose the expert.
You can have the expert choose the token.
So each expert picks their favorite tokens,
or you can have each token pick their favorite experts.
Or you can, somehow, have this very complicated router
that globally decides, oh, yes, you, token, should
go to this expert.
And this other token should go to that other experts
to try to globally optimize assignments.
So basically, almost all the MoE do token choice TopK.
And so the token is going to be the one to choose the experts.
And there's going to be k different experts that
get selected to be in the pool.
And you can see, this is from the OlMoE paper,
differences between token choice and expert choice.
You see that token choice is going
to get lower validation losses, higher downstream benchmark
scores compared to expert choice.
There have been successful expert choice models.
I mean, this also trains fine.
But token choice has generally been much easier to get working
and has been the standard for all of the models
that we see today.
I think one of the four models was maybe expert choice.
But I don't think that's necessarily
a strong vote of confidence.
I think that was one of the unreleased Llama 4
models in my defense.
OK.
So I think there are many different ways
that you can do routing.
So one of the ways that you can do routing
is, you can actually have a small linear projection
that says, OK, I'm going to get my input.
My router is going to compute an inner product.
Each expert has a vector direction.
And the closest in inner product space will get selected.
This is, by far, the most common router.
It's used in the classic Switch Transformer, the GShard.
Those two are the early Google papers.
It's used in Grok, Mixtral, DBRX, DeepSeek, and others.
The number of k that you choose varies, depending on which paper
you're looking at.
But for the most part, you're just taking inner products.
One thing that has always been a little mysterious to me
is that many, many papers have shown that actually, you don't
need to do any learned routing.
You can just take your X's, you can hash them and send them
to different feedforward networks.
And actually, this is fine too.
This gives gains, not as much as TopK,
but somehow, hashing-based expert routing is also something
that people do.
Common baseline in papers, not used in deployment
for many reasons.
You can do RL to learn the routes.
You can basically have a router that's an inner product router.
And you can use reinforcement learning
to try to treat this router as a kind of policy
and then learn it.
If you're a machine learning classic learning
theory-type oriented person, I think
this should be the natural way to think about the problem.
You're like, OK, what am I doing?
It's a bandit problem.
I'm selecting one out of k or k out of n.
And I don't observe all of them.
This is a bandit problem.
I will use a bandit or an RL algorithm.
Used in some of the earliest work, because this is the natural way to think about the problem,
like Bengio in 2013.
But it is not a common approach.
And I think the reason why it's not common
is because the approaches needed to do RL introduce
a lot of overhead in terms of both the RL algorithm
and the stochasticity.
And what people have figured out is,
there's a good set of heuristics,
these recipes that you can apply to this very simple classic TopK
routing scheme that basically just has it working right.
And so there's no reason to do something much more complicated.
I will finally mention an idea that I think is really cool
and that I love as a person that likes things that make sense.
You can solve a linear assignment problem,
where you say, OK, I'm going to globally compute the score that
says like, oh, it would be this good for this token
to go to that expert.
So you compute all these pairwise scores
of how good the assignments are.
And you can use linear assignment
to exactly solve for the optimal assignment
from experts to tokens.
It's been shown to do good things in some cases,
hasn't been seen at scale at all.
I would think, because it's extremely expensive
relative to the others to get working.
So TopK routing, as I said, is basically the consensus
routing mechanism.
How does this work?
It's very, very simple.
And if you were paying attention in the DSA slide,
this looks a lot like DSA.
You will also notice this if you were reading some other papers like H-Nets
or these other kinds of things.
This will appear in many different places.
So this is a good kind of pattern to be able to recognize.
So what you're doing is, you are going to take in your inputs.
And you're going to take it through a feed forward.
And then I'm going to compute some sort of scores.
And the scores that I'm going to compute
is going to be the softmax between the experts
and my inputs u.
And then this s is going to be the scores.
And I'm going to select the TopK of those guys.
And that's going to be the gate that's going
to control each of my experts.
So this is like input.
This is the residual term.
This is the FFN.
I've got gates.
And the gates are controlled TopK.
This is the equation form of what you
would imagine of a TopK router.
And the only detail that you're probably learning here
is, how do I learn my gates?
My gates are just learned by taking
inner product between a weight for each expert and the inputs
that I have.
Very, very lightweight.
So there's nothing complicated about the ways
that I'm going to select my gates.
Even within this simple thing, there's
been some innovation and variation from DeepSeek and friends.
DeepSeekMoE pioneered this idea, which is now very widely used,
called Shared Experts.
This is a very intuitive idea, where in the classic TopK
router, you would have k different-- or sorry,
in this case, n different experts.
And these experts, you would select amongst them.
But sometimes, you might say, well,
there's some very common processing
that I want to apply to all tokens.
Maybe you don't want experts to be different every time.
You want some experts to always be applied
and then some other experts to be applied conditionally.
So what DeepSeekMoE did was, they
took the original expert design.
They cut up the experts into smaller, finer grained chunks.
And some subset of those fine grained experts
were as shared experts that are always on.
So these bypass the router.
They always process our inputs.
And they go back on the outputs.
Sorry.
And this is a nice idea, because it turned out
that if you had this classic expert design,
you were just reusing a lot of these weights
to do common modeling.
And so you can offload this into the one shared expert,
letting these guys specialize even more.
And as I was kind of saying, DeepSeek
is really nice in that they do careful ablations
in a lot of their papers.
And so they have this very nice ablation,
where they look at zero shared experts
and then you have these big experts, 16 routed experts.
And this is really the old GShard Google design,
compared to, they have very fine grained segmentation
of experts and one shared expert amongst these.
And as you make the experts smaller and smaller,
and you have one shared expert, you
see significant gains from both of those interventions.
And for some of these, the shared expert
has very significant improvements,
like TriviaQA, NaturalQuestions.
This blue to yellow gap, right, is shared experts or not.
So more experts, shared experts, all generally seem to help.
And if you want more validation of these claims and ideas,
you see this from OlMoE as well.
OlMoE is, I think, the nice Western carefully controlled MoE
study.
They do things like, oh, do shared experts help?
They conclude that shared experts don't help very much.
And number of experts, they show,
doing fine-grained, many experts is helpful.
So they disagree a little bit on the shared expert point,
but they also have very nice, carefully controlled ablations.
Many of the recent MoE do follow essentially the DeepSeek design.
There were a couple of early MoEs up until this point.
The first three, I keep giving Google
praise for doing lots of interesting things.
The first three were from Google,
Mixtral, DBRX, and Grok were some of the early MoE
attempts in the West.
DeepSeek v1 comes up with both the fine-grained and shared
expert design.
And then that catches on, and everyone else
follows from DeepSeek.
I mean, it's a similar, I would say,
phenomenon to the Llama design for dense transformers
being essentially, the standard DeepSeekMoE and DeepSeek v3
are the standard design that people have copied
for the MoE side of things.
And if you look at Qwen 3.5, or GLM, or any
of these modern models, you continue
to see both shared experts and fine-grained experts
in widespread use amongst all of these people.
And so that's been a very battle-tested design.
Any questions?
Oh, yes.
Good.
Yeah.
If there is a shared expert or there are few shared experts,
how would parallelization work in that case?
Yeah.
So in the shared expert case, you
wouldn't get any parallelization savings.
Every activation has to route through those.
You can copy the shared expert to basically eat memory savings
to reduce comms cost.
Cool.
All right.
So that's the design space of routers.
Now, I want to talk about training MoEs.
And it gets into really surprising,
and I would say, very deep learning things about this.
I think, initially, when I was learning about MoEs,
I thought, there's no way that we can train these things well
or reasonably.
But it turns out, there are lots of tricks
that when combined together, just really work well
and robustly for some reason.
So as we'll raise in the previous question,
we don't want to activate all the experts during training,
because if we do that, we're going to pay the full flops
cost of all of our experts.
And we have a lot of experts.
So we need sparsity for efficiency at training time.
But if we have sparsity, then gating decisions
are no longer differentiable.
And we also don't see all of the different counterfactual experts
we could have picked.
So these are both big problems.
So there are different solutions.
We could use RL to optimize our gating policies.
I already mentioned this, not super popular.
You could do things like stochastic perturbations.
So if you're familiar with explore, exploit, bandit style
stuff, you could do some of that.
Now, the third one is, you could have
a whole bunch of weird heuristics
that deal with the fact that the gating decisions are
sparse to balance out which experts go where.
Guess which one people use in practice?
I've been hinting at this.
It's number 3.
It's a collection of really interesting heuristics
that end up working.
I'll talk about the other two first.
They're not widely used.
I would open with that.
But I think it's useful to know.
So some people have done, this is
from Clark 2020, research on things like,
can you use RL to learn routers?
So it does work.
You can use RL, this is the green line over here.
That's one of the baseline approaches.
It works fine.
But because of the gradient variance and complexity,
it's not actually the optimal thing to do.
And even some of the approaches that are proposed in this paper
handily beat using reinforced gradients for routing decisions.
Now, something that's very close to the idea of RL
but starts to move more towards this heuristic world of write
down objectives and try things is this idea
of a stochastic approximation.
And it comes from the earliest MoE paper from Noam, Shazeer,
and others, where what you do is,
you don't really make a hard decision during training.
What you do is you make stochastic decisions.
So what you do is, you still have this routing setup.
So this H is, you have the inner product between your parameters
and your inputs.
This is your standard routing inner product.
But then, instead of just doing this,
I'm going to inject some noise that's
dependent on the scale of the input.
And then that's going to be my H.
And now, I'm going to keep the TopK and softmax, just like I
was explaining with TopK.
And then that's going to be the output that
goes in to my TopK function.
Now, if you look at this, what is this doing?
Well, it just means that if you have two experts that
are closely tied or it's very close to each other,
then stochastically, you'll pick one of them and not the other.
And as you backprop, you're going to backprop in a way
that the experts that are helpful will get high weights.
So this perturbation allows you to tie break and explore
a little bit more.
And hopefully, the gradient structure
is such that, if an expert is helpful,
it's going to emphasize that expert more,
and it will get higher and higher weights in general.
So this is one reasonable thing that you can do.
It leads to experts that are a bit more robust.
And the softmax allows you to learn how
to rank all these k experts.
Rather than just doing a hard selection of TopK,
you're weighting by these elements.
There's another scheme that's very closely related that's
done in Fedus, et al., in 2022, which
does a uniform, multiplicative perturbation.
They do this for the reason of hardening the experts,
making them robust.
This was a useful thing to do, but this was later
removed in later Google papers that do routing.
And it's not really clear that this is necessary at all.
You see later ablation showing that not
doing any of these stochastic or robustness tricks
actually helps with both stability and overall quality
of the final trained MoE.
So this suggests you don't need necessarily
the stochastic exploration terms.
So this takes us to what you actually do,
which is a series of heuristics that, in the end,
is going to give us a working MoE.
And a lot of these have to do with essentially balancing.
So what's the problem if you just do normal gradient descent,
ignoring any of these exploration-exploitation concerns?
Well, what's going to happen is, you're
going to first route your TopK experts.
And then the strongest of those experts will get more signal.
Your backprop is going to say, that expert was good.
You increase the weight of that expert, move
that parameter closer to that.
So you get this rich-gets-richer effect, where
experts that are chosen get very strong weights.
Strong weights means that they're selected more often.
And they run away, taking on everything.
And so this expert collapse phenomenon or expert starvation
phenomenon is a very, very real problem.
And in some sense, this is the core issue
that you have to solve with heuristic training of MoEs.
And so what do you do?
Well, what you do is, you add a heuristic loss
to the total modeling loss.
And this loss is supposed to balance out the tokens that
go to different experts.
And one approach, which is done in the Switch
Transformer over here, you can look at what this does.
You have different experts going from 1 to n
And you have a batch of tokens.
And what you want to do is, you want
to make sure that these two inner products are small.
OK.
So what is happening here?
F is the fraction of tokens that are dispatched
to any single expert.
And then P of I is the softer version.
This is not just whether the token is dispatched
to an expert, this is the total probability mass
of the router that's allocated.
And you multiply these two terms.
And this is, at least to me, not a thing,
where you would derive it from first principles.
I think the easiest way to see what this thing is doing
is to take the derivative of this object.
So if you take the derivative of this with respect to P of I--
and P of I, remember, is the probability mass allocated
to an expert, well, the derivative
is going to be the fraction of tokens that are allocated.
So in some sense, you can think of this as a penalty
in the gradient space, where the more tokens you get,
the more negative gradient you get.
So this is trying to push down the probability mass
on very popular experts proportional to their fraction.
And that's the action of this loss.
That's the way to think about it.
So the objective itself in equation 4
might not be clear to start with,
but once you reason about the action of the gradient,
it becomes clear what this is trying to do,
which is to push down popular experts.
So then we can actually take these ideas and essentially
reconstruct DeepSeek v1 and 2's MoE system.
So what do you do to build DeepSeekMoE?
Well, you're going to do your normal losses.
And you're just going to backprop straight
through the experts, ignoring all this nondifferentiability
and exploration concerns.
But you're going to add per expert balancing that's
identical to the switch transformer, what I just showed you.
So you're going to have this loss that
multiplies F, which is the fraction,
and P, which is the total mass.
But DeepSeek folks, they're very savvy with their systems design,
so they don't just balance the experts,
they also want to balance by device.
So if your experts are allocated to some devices-- so let's say,
my machine over here has four experts, this machine over here
has another four experts, you want those two machines
to be balanced, so both of them are running at full utilization.
So you don't want to just make the experts even,
you also want to ensure that the devices are even.
So this is a secondary objective.
It acts in exactly the same way.
If you look at the function here instead of experts,
you're just operating on each device's fraction,
you apply the secondary device balancing loss,
just for utilization reasons.
In DeepSeek v3, they have a per expert bias term that they use.
And they use an online learning trick to balance out experts,
getting rid of some of these auxiliary losses,
but they do, in the end, have to add
some of these auxiliary losses in order
to ensure extreme imbalances don't happen.
So I think, I add this as a side note that DeepSeek v3
and others have started to get rid of some of these,
I would say, uglier auxiliary losses,
but there's no solution that fully gets rid of them so far.
The last thing I'll talk about with load balancing losses
is, you might ask, do I need to deal with this?
It's all a bunch of complicated heuristics.
I wish I could just get rid of the load balancing loss.
But if you remove the load balancing loss,
the effects are pretty catastrophic.
These are both from the OlMoE paper, where
they do this nice ablation of removing the load balancing
loss entirely.
If you have the load balancing loss,
you get this pink line at the top, very nice normal curves.
Remove the load balancing loss, your losses significantly
increase, and your training loss also is not doing so well.
Maybe more tellingly, if you look
at which experts are doing what, with load balancing
and without load balancing, that's
these bottom panels over here, you
see a really, really stark difference.
Without load balancing, almost all the tokens
are going to two experts-- the yellow expert
and the pinkish expert that you see here.
Whereas if you have the load balancing loss,
even though we had this kind of heuristic thing going on,
all of these experts are being utilized across the token.
So we have this nice, even utilization.
So we do see that the load balancing
loss does what we expect.
And without it, we've thrown away a ton of parameters.
Those experts are doing absolutely nothing
for most of training.
So this is how MoEs are trained.
And I think, just to go back, this is pretty surprising to me,
that you've got this thing that's nondifferentiable,
you're doing this TopK selection.
And it is, honestly, a pretty complicated object,
and all you really need to do is to just add this balancing
loss to even out the experts.
And then the rest of it, you treat it
as if you can just pump gradients through the system,
and the model trains very nicely.
And I think a big part of this is,
this dynamic that if an expert is useful,
you're going to reinforce it.
And that's a positive reinforcement cycle
that's nicely balanced out by evening things out.
Those two dynamics cancel each other out.
Cool.
Oh, and the final thing I'll say is, that same trick
is used in DSA.
We already saw the TopK thing.
It's used in things like H-Nets.
If you're familiar with that, that
was a temp to remove tokenizers.
And so I think you'll see this trick more often
in the future, where this idea of TopK selection
and using load balancing or other kinds of auxiliary losses
to enable that nondifferentiability
will be an ingredient of future architecture design.
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] mixture of experts is like a systems optimization.
But if you actually exploit, can you look at them?
Are they actually doing something in different domains?
Yeah.
So some papers have a visualization of which tokens
are activated by which experts.
And because the routers are so simple,
it's not like, experts are like smart experts.
They're not like medical experts, legal experts, or whatever.
You do see that certain tokens are routed to different things,
like punctuations might be routed
to one expert or other symbols might be routed to one expert,
non-English language character sets
might be routed to another expert.
But it's not really something where you can look at it
and be like, oh, this is the Wall Street Journal
expert or something, nothing like that.
There's no semantics of maybe one way of putting it.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, the per expert loss, in principle, if it's perfectly
enforced, will also enforce a per device balancing
if your experts are evenly split.
But I think, at least my interpretation of that
is, you don't want to crank up the per expert loss so high
that you get true full uniformity,
because that has deleterious effects on training dynamics.
But per device is important enough
that you're willing to add on a little bit of extra loss
to encourage per device balancing over others.
Cool.
OK.
So now, I'm going to talk a little bit about the system side
of things before we wrap up.
So training MoEs has additional fun systems dynamics
that are introduced.
When I talk about parallelism, I'm
mostly going to talk about the standard, let's call it,
forms of parallelism.
You can split up your data over many small chunks.
You can take your one data set and split it up
over many machines.
You can do model parallelism, where you can take your model,
and maybe you can split up your model over different machines.
And you can combine those two in various ways,
you can, of course, do that.
But I think the thing that we realize
is that each of those parallelism techniques has some limit.
For data parallelism, you're maxed out your batch size.
Once you hit your batch size, you can't parallelize by data
anymore.
For model size, there's natural cut points,
where you can cut your model.
Once you exhaust those, you can't parallelize anymore.
If you combine this with expert parallelism,
you get another additional nice access to parallelize on.
And when you do this, a lot of the underlying implementations
for this allow you to take advantage of sparse matrix
multiply that has been built into GPUs.
So another thing that I'll mention
is, if you have multiple experts, let's say, on one GPU,
one way of thinking about it is to say,
I'm going to have multiple small matrix multiplies.
But this is not nice, because you ideally
want these bigger matrix multiplies,
where you can reuse caches and do all sorts of things.
So instead, what you can do is, you
can nicely leverage sparsity.
And block diagonal, of course, is the most basic form,
but you can use much more complicated forms
of structured sparsity that are natively supported in hardware
to allow you to essentially multiply
experts and inputs in very, very clean ways, very fast.
So this is another reason why MoEs are nice.
If you think about the computation patterns of MoEs,
they almost correspond to these kinds of structured matrix
multiplications that are very easy and efficient to support
in hardware.
So there's this hardware architecture codesign
that's happening with MoEs.
And in terms of parallelism, one thing I'll mention,
this is a very recent development.
This is from Nemotron-3.
I forgot who asked this question.
When we do this expert parallelism,
we have to be shipping activations from device
to device in order to say like, oh, you belong in that expert,
I need to ship you over.
That can result in significant communications overhead.
So some of the things that people have started
to think about is to say, well, my shared expert, which
I'm not going to communicate, this can be in big dimensions.
But my experts, I need to communicate those activations,
I want those to be in smaller lower dimensional vectors.
So you might actually take your residual stream
and downproject it first, and then
decide to do the collective communication call of sending
this activation out.
And that will significantly save on communication
without fully having the drawbacks of having a smaller
hidden dimension size.
So you can actually do these kind of projection tricks
to nicely control the trade-off of communication
and having your MoEs parallelized.
One final trivia, let's call it detail of MoEs
that I think is fun, but it has been solved in recent years,
is stochasticity.
If you do MoE infrastructure naively, what you'll find
is that, unless your experts are perfectly balanced on your input
distribution, you'll find that certain experts might be
much more popular than others.
And if some expert like, let's say, in this case,
expert 0 is just a really popular expert,
you're going to actually start running into situations where
this expert queue of tokens just starts building up, and building up.
And eventually, you'll get to a point, where you say,
my queue is so long, I have to start dropping tokens.
And the earlier generation of MoE
inference infrastructure and code,
a lot of what happened was, you would just actually
silently drop this expert.
And you just proceed on with your computation
as if nothing had happened.
You just send a zero back and pretend that that was fine.
And this means that you can have these weird stochasticities,
where if other users sent in queries that
hit the experts that you're using, then
you could actually get a worse result,
because they would bump you out of the expert queue.
These kinds of very strange things can happen.
But these days, they drop less architectures
that have gotten rid of a lot of these issues.
So this is no longer really an issue.
So mega blocks and other very common open source MoE
frameworks don't have this issue anymore.
So the last thing that I'll talk about in terms
of the design of MoEs is this issue of stability.
We've already talked about stability issues
in the context of architecture design last lecture.
But if you remember what I said then,
I said exponentials are bad, divisions are bad,
which means softmaxes are danger zone for stability issues.
Now, what we done with mixture of experts?
Well, we have introduced yet another softmax in the routing,
because we're going to do TopK.
We're going to do softmax.
And that's going to be how we route to experts.
Now, people have long noticed that the softmax operation
in MoEs are potentially very, very dangerous.
Barret Zoph and others, in the early days of Google MoE design,
had an entire paper on MoE stability.
And this was one of the things that they noticed.
And I'm going to go into some of the details.
You'll see the solution fairly often
for some of the more sensitive and tricky parts.
You might end up using something like Float 32
for just the expert router.
You might have a z-loss as well here.
We've talked about z-loss before in order
to control the softmax stability issues that we saw.
Z-loss, I think, was quite popular, actually,
to do MoE router stability even in the early days.
OlMoE, which I've been talking about extensively,
has done ablations on adding or removing z-loss.
It's quite clear, from these very spiky training loss
curves, that z-loss on the router can be quite helpful.
There are other issues with MoEs that you can end up with.
And I think you probably all have experienced this maybe
recently if you work with language models, which
is that MoEs can be pretty annoying to fine tune.
They have so many parameters that if you're
trying to fine tune the experts, you actually
end up with very serious overfitting issues.
So you can see that if you have your dense models,
train and val are fairly close, they don't overfit crazily.
But if you look at the sparse, train and val gap
is extremely large, as you fine tune
these models, or, in this case, downstream task.
I think it was one of the glue benchmark tasks.
Now, you could have a case, where you fine tune
non-MoE feed forwards.
You could also fine tune just attention.
These are pretty common interventions that people do,
especially the attention fine-tuning
is something that I see quite often with MoE works recently.
But if your model has non-MoE layers, then, of course,
you can also just fine tune those.
And there is often others, we're kind of arguing for those.
And of course, there's also the bitter lesson version
of this, which is, maybe you should just
use 1.4 million examples instead of whatever number you have.
If you have a lot of data, you can retrain, basically,
the MoE entirely during your fine-tuning stage.
And you won't have quite as much of a generalization gap.
OK.
The last MoE-specific trick that I'll mention
is this idea of upcycling.
This has actually become a lot less popular in the last year.
I don't think I've seen a single upcycled model this year.
But it's a cool idea.
And also, there were some very nice models
earlier on using this trick.
So I want to mention this.
So upcycling is this idea that if you want a MoE,
maybe you can just take a dense model that you've trained,
and then you can instantiate a MoE based on that dense model.
And the idea is, you just copy everything, including the MLPs.
You just make a whole bunch of copies from these MLPs.
You have a router, which have a random initialization.
And then you just train this model.
And if you do this, then because of the stochasticity of which
inputs go to where and the MLP, you're
going to get these experts that start to specialize.
And in the end, you'll actually end up with MoE.
And in some of the earliest papers that proposed upcycling,
they show that an upcycled method
could get much better language modeling,
in this case, accuracy, performance,
upcycling a dense model rather than continuing
to train the same model, which is
a cool thing that you can show.
People have validated this at scale in many ways.
So many CPM is another Chinese model that I quite like,
because they do a lot of carefully controlled ablations.
They had a MoE, where they took their miniCPM 2.4b model.
They upcycled it to a 13.4 billion parameter model.
And they got a bunch of almost free wins from doing that.
Qwen also, when they did their Qwen MoE,
initialize from there 1.8B Qwen model.
They upcycled that to a Qwen 1.5.A, 2.7B model.
And they ended up with one of the first
and one of the very high performance models.
It's, I think, one of the first larger scale
upcycling successes.
Of course, these days, I don't think
anyone's really upcycling anymore,
because you don't really train dense models
and then convert them.
You might as well just train your big hero run
on an MoE to start with.
So I don't think we see this quite as much,
but I wanted to mention this, because I
think it's an important thing to know
in the action space of mixture of experts models.
OK.
So the last thing I want to end with is,
I want to just walk us through the DeepSeek
models-- v1, v2, and v3.
I think there's a lot to learn from the evolution of DeepSeek
models.
And also, if you're interested, just
in general about MoEs or architecture design,
I would encourage that you read the DeepSeek papers.
I think they're very well written.
I think they have a lot of details
that are worth digging into.
So the DeepSeekMoE architecture at v1
is already, actually, the prototype
of a lot of different modern MoE.
It's got the shared and fine-grained expert structure.
It uses standard TopK routing with the auxiliary loss
balancing.
I mean, in some ways, I would say,
this is like the prototypical platonic ideal of MoE model.
DeepSeekMoE v2 scales this guy up.
So you've got two shared experts, many more fine-grained
experts.
And you've got this device routing component,
and you've got a communication balancing component.
Both of these are essentially adding auxiliary losses
to optimize systems.
I think it's important to realize that successful language
model training is not just about deep learning,
it's also about really respecting your systems.
So DeepSeek v2 is really a reflection, I think,
of this philosophy.
And then in DeepSeekMoE v3, they've still
got the shared and fine-grained experts design,
but they've got different ways of doing balancing.
They've gotten aux-loss-free ways
of balancing the different experts.
And they've switched to using sigmoid plus softmax, which
is a different way of weighting their experts, but really,
mostly similar.
Finally, since we're already here,
we might as well just walk through the rest
of DeepSeekMoE V3.
They've got lots of other cool things.
I'm a big fan of how they think about systems.
They've got multihead latent attention,
where instead of doing QKV directly,
what you're going to do is you're
going to represent them as this lower dimensional latent c.
So you have your hidden input.
Instead of directly producing your Qs, Ks, and Vs,
you're going to first produce the c.
And then you're going to produce your Q, Ks, and Vs
as a function of that.
And that allows you to get significantly improved savings.
Instead of KV caching all your Ks and Vs,
I only need to store these Cs.
And the Cs are hopefully, lower dimensional.
And that's why it's called MLA, latent activation,
because the Cs, which are latent,
are the KV cache quantities that you need to save.
The only complexity that you might need to worry about
is that this is going to conflict with rope
when you do KV caching.
So you have to be a little bit careful about how you rotate
different dimensions and so on.
And so the trick is, you have non-latent dimensions
that encode positions, but I'm not
going to go into too much more details about that.
Finally, something that I thought
was a very cool idea for MoE, actually,
DeepSeekMoE v3, but hasn't caught on very much,
is the idea of MTP or multitoken prediction.
Instead of predicting one future token,
you predict multiple tokens all at once.
That has a statistical argument for why that's a good idea.
Maybe it lets you predict the future a little bit better.
But also, there's this nice systems argument
that you now have a speculative decoder built in.
Percy will talk about that when he talks about inference later,
but it's just a trick that you can use to speed up
your decoding from your model.
OK.
I think we're roughly at time.
So to put everything together, right,
MoEs are this very clever idea to take advantage of sparsity,
so that you can have more parameters than you're paying for.
So you don't pay for the compute cost of all of your parameters,
but you are getting the parameter benefits.
You might initially think that this kind of routing problem
is very hard, but it turns out that very simple things
work well, even at scale.
And at this point, it's clear that MoEs are here to stay,
so you should understand how they work and what they are.
Thanks.